### **ROSSLYN SADIA-MUTAHI**

Bachelor of Arts, Certified Green Belt, Certified Public Accountant, ISO 9001 Lead Auditor



Contacts: +254 720 758617 / +254 734 800547 / rwaduma@gmail.com

#### **Summary of Experience**

I am an operations and process improvement practitioner with over 19 years' experience in the implementation of process excellence strategies across diverse industries including shipping and logistics, human resources management, education and training, architecture and construction.

Since process excellence emphasizes making decisions with data, all the process improvement positions I have held, by design, necessitate performance monitoring and analysis of data to aid in optimal decision making.

I support organisations to design efficient and effective systems that improve quality and increase productivity and profitability.

#### **Personal Objectives**

- To consistently act with honour, stay true to my word and be authentic.
- To engage with organisations that seek to break down complex issues to arrive at solutions that benefit the organisation and its clients.
- To aid organisations in making better decisions and driving the right internal behaviour by setting up and monitoring the right processes and measures.

#### **Career Experience**

### **September 2013 to present**

#### Lead Consultant; Top Tier Limited

This is an independent management consulting role in which I work with organisations to:

- Monitor performance of key results and process measures for organisations and departments to identify the need for improvements.
- Set up organisational systems and structures, including policies, processes, procedures, work instructions, etc.
- Perform system audits to confirm that processes are performing as they were designed to perform.
- Review or design or streamline, then implement work processes.
- Work with organisations to implement the quality management system standard, ISO 9001.

## **April 2012 to September 2013**

#### Independent Consultant

• Work with organisations to implement the quality management system standard, ISO 9001.

#### December 2009 to March 2012

# Project Leader & Financial Business Partner; Maersk Kenya Limited

- Responsible for selection and monitoring of key performance indicators for the top functional leaders in the organisation.
- Monitoring and analysis of financial information and combining this with business information and market realities to provide recommendations to different departments (functions) on profitable and loss-giving business, opportunities to increase cost recoveries and reduce operational costs.
- Accountable for aligning Maersk Kenya finance processes to standard global, company-wide processes and for their transfer to a centralised service centre. The role included communication with internal stakeholders on changes in job roles and change management in general, and coordination of work between the local office and the service centre.

Resume: Rosslyn Waduma Sadia

Member of a team responsible for the implementation of a customised invoicing, accounts receivables and dispute management system built on an SAP platform. The role was responsible for communication, training, data integrity, management of local risks & exceptions, and hyper care after go-live.

#### September 2007 to November 2009

## Process Excellence Manager; Maersk Kenya Limited

- Responsible for creating and nurturing a mindset of continuous improvement of processes within the core functions of Customer Service, Operations, Finance and Sales.
- Coaching functional managers in their implementation and maintenance of process changes and performance.
- Training in tools of process excellence.
- Measuring process performance and ensuring that any process improvements include the customers' perspective and therefore, meet customer requirements.
- Working with a cross-functional team, applied lean principles to improve out-turn of imports documents for customers from an average of 24 hours to an average of 90 minutes.
- Monitoring and analysis of process performance of the accounts receivable process. With this
  information, made recommendations that reinforced the decision to set up a team to handle
  customer disputes with regard to receivables.

### October 2005 to August 2007

### Assistant Manager & Manager, Service Delivery; Maersk Kenya Limited

- Monitoring data quality through audits and participating in initiatives to increase data quality and output accuracy.
- Monitoring service performance to ensure that the company could respond quickly to customer, management and shareholder concerns.
- Responsible for monitoring and analysing data arising out of customer and organisation staff
  interactions to identify opportunities for service improvement, find solutions and drive
  implementation of agreed solutions.
- Accountable for identification of recurrent service failures and their root cause; responsible for following up on their resolution to minimise avoidable operational costs and increase service effectiveness.
- Responsible for the implementation of customer operations management systems.

### September 2004 to September 2005

#### Assistant Manager, Customer Service; Maersk Kenya Limited

- Responsible for training and support of Customer Service staff.
- Managing the shipping line's documentation and invoicing of inbound and outbound shipments, including Kenya Customs and Kenya Ports Authority manifests.
- Overall responsible for shipment data quality.
- In conjunction with the Imports Supervisor and Kenya Revenue Authority (KRA), successfully implemented the automated system of the Revenue Authority, Tradex.

#### February 2004 to August 2004

#### Senior Accountant, Maersk Kenya Limited

 Analysed the manual invoicing process of a key revenue stream and successfully managed the implementation an automated invoicing system to enable the transitioning of the process to a service centre for centralised and effective management.

#### Other positions

- February 2002 to January 2004; Assistant Manager, Customer Service; Maersk India PVT Limited
- February 1999 to January 2002; Management Trainee; Maersk Kenya Limited

#### Skills

- Monitoring, analysis and reporting
- Change and stakeholder management
- Process monitoring, analysis and improvement

- Team leadership coaching and training
- Facilitation of training programmes
- Use and explanation of control charts to measure and understand process performance
- Financial accounting, interpretation and reporting
- Management of quality
- Proficiency in MS Excel

#### **Education and Professional Development**

## Degree and Professional Training

- Bachelor of Arts, Economics and Mathematics, 1999; GPA 3.05/4.00; (Egerton University, Njoro, Kenya)
- Certified Public Accountant, 2008 (Kenya Accountants & Secretaries National Examination Board)

## Maersk Line and Maersk Kenya Ltd

- European Computer Driving Licence Certificate, 2001
- Maersk International Shipping Education, 2001
- Coaching Others, 2007
- Maersk Greenbelt (Process Excellence), 2008
- Assistant Coach Development, 2009

### Additional Training

- Predictive Index Management, 2004 (PI International)
- Media Training, 2006 (Gina Din Communications)
- Editing and Style, 2010 (CAN-DO! Company)
- Quality Management Systems (QMS) Lead Auditor (A17024), 2012 (Bureau Veritas)

#### **Professional Memberships**

- Institute of Certified Public Accountants of Kenya (ICPAK)
- Organisation of Women in International Trade (OWIT)
- The Founders Network